<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-05-28T21:58:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Memories</title><subtitle>. . .</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Vipassana</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/19/vipassana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vipassana" /><published>2018-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/05/19/vipassana</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/19/vipassana.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently attended my first ten-day Vipassana retreat through
dhamma.org. Students are prohibited from taking notes but I jotted some down
the day I returned, for future reference. Here they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading, writing, music, communication with others, use of technology,
and any sort of stimulus is prohibited. We meditated for ten hours a day. As
a result my sense of time was greatly expanded: the retreat felt much longer
than ten days; the first two days felt like an eternity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I experienced many out-of-the-blue flashes of emotional memories from my
early childhood. E.g., video games, play dates at friends’ houses, recess
on the elementary school playground. Most of these experiences I enjoyed a
lot and thus craved while reminiscing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Occasionally other emotional memories also came to mind without much
prompting. E.g., experiences with past lovers, and experiences with my
parents. Some were happy and others unhappy. The main ones that made me
experience cravings were sexual; most others did not affect me.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge was dealing with the recurring feeling of wanting to
leave as soon as possible. I spent the first week mostly not looking forward
to meditating and the lizard part of my brain spun up stories to make the
sits more bearable, to make the next break arrive as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other aversions to the experience included FOMO and disagreements with the
teachings. E.g., Goenka talks about subatomic particles being composed of eight
elements, four mental and four physical (which of course are fire, earth,
air, and water). He also alludes to reincarnation. I found myself wishing
he used less religious terminology, but ultimately I’m unsure that matters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I practiced not believing my thoughts a lot. The stories my brain generates
about myself and others are not reality; they are limited views of multifaceted
subjects and often distortions of reality. Goenka had a useful model for
thinking of one kind of story: what we see when we look at our friend Joe
is not really Joe, but a model of him we place in front of him, with our
impressions projected onto him. (And similarly for oneself.) A large benefit
of meditating for 100 hours is that I spent a lot of time being aware of these
models. Similarly, a lot of my internal struggles are the result of stories
I have convinced myself are true: e.g., my friend Bob is so smart and suave,
and ugh, what can I do to be more like him? I didn’t necessarily “root
cause” these problems or stories while meditating (the point is to observe
one’s sensations), but I did gain awareness of the fact that many of my
problems are ultimately tied to some kind of story.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I gained a lot of experience calming myself down during stressful or
otherwise heavily emotional moments, as well as boosting my confidence
and seeing the glass half full. A recurring narrative when going through
difficult periods was something like, “Well, I’m stuck with this, so
I might as well lean into it and become stronger,” or, “This situation
will feel a lot less terrible if I force myself to see the good in it.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I gained a deeper sense of impermanence. I experienced my thoughts and
feelings passing when I observe and don’t get caught up in them. This is
easy to intellectualize but I have a different appreciation for it after
100 hours of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was grateful for the break from technology. I realized I often scroll
mindlessly through various apps on my phone or through reddit posts on
my laptop, simply because my mind wants to not exert effort yet wants to
feel like it’s absorbing something useful or interesting. I constantly
confronted this laziness while meditating. Now that I’m again immersed
in technology I find it easier to control my instinct to reach for my phone
or type “reddit” into my browser, and I can focus on a task for longer
without “needing” to take a break.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought a lot about work and discipline. I don’t know how applicable my
meditation practice is to other areas of life, but I repeatedly thought that
perhaps every worthwhile venture is like meditation. That is, the majority of
the retreat was grueling, but there were a few extremely peaceful or positive
moments, and the resulting realizations were extremely rewarding. Could
this be the case for every worthwhile activity? That is, could it be the
case that, often it’s mostly uncomfortable and not fun in the moment,
but is rewarding after having put in a couple dozen hours of serious effort?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The day I returned I felt less social anxiety than I normally do, and I
felt much more emotionally grounded than usual. Now that it’s been a few
days I can feel the anxiety cropping up again, but I feel more aware of it,
and that it is not necessarily “me”. It doesn’t feel like my brain
works any differently or is better at problem-solving, but I still feel I
can sustain my focus for longer than I could before.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The day I returned, social interactions felt smoother but also more
dream-like and surreal than usual. This has faded.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought a lot more about compassion and felt a lot more compassion as
a result of the sits. My awareness increased partly because Goenka spent a
good amount of time talking about it during the discourses. Compassion and
empathy are certainly areas of improvement for me so I’m happy to have
stronger gut feelings now.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having typed all that out, I wonder again whether it was worthwhile and whether
I would do another one. I still think it was and that I would. The biggest
take-aways were: increased confidence, more awareness of my attention and my
mental and physical states, and more acceptance of myself and my progress
through life’s various games. I would like to revisit my thoughts on the
retreat in another few weeks for a hopefully different perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently attended my first ten-day Vipassana retreat through dhamma.org. Students are prohibited from taking notes but I jotted some down the day I returned, for future reference. Here they are.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Time</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/11/time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time" /><published>2018-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/04/11/time</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/11/time.html">&lt;p&gt;Don’t let other people waste your time. Don’t let yourself waste your time. Your time is all you have. You need to respect yourself more. Be firm; if others are offended or they don’t understand, they’re not worth spending time with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t idolize anyone; be careful of the halo effect. Someone’s photo reel – whether in person or digital – is not a representative sample of their life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Don’t let other people waste your time. Don’t let yourself waste your time. Your time is all you have. You need to respect yourself more. Be firm; if others are offended or they don’t understand, they’re not worth spending time with.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Principles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/08/memories.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Principles" /><published>2018-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/04/08/memories</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/08/memories.html">&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with some Maslow-inspired principles, in no order of significance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acknowledge your humanity; i.e., if something feels off, consult this list.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exercise a moderate amount every day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep enough every day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eat well and in moderation; do not overeat or indulge in unnatural foods or drinks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not use drugs; use only small amounts of caffeine from tea.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spend time outside every day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spend time with others; meet new people and nurture important relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give your time and attention; be part of something beyond yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish to live by these principles every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are occasionally days which, for whatever reason – often failing to plan – lack actions from one or more of these categories. On such days I wish to notice the off-balance feeling, refer to the first principle, and fix the error.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Let’s start with some Maslow-inspired principles, in no order of significance:</summary></entry></feed>